<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<glossary
	version="5.0"
	xml:id="glossary"
	xml:lang="en"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	>
	
	<title>Glossary</title>
	
	<glossentry xml:id="glossary.auto_increment">
		<glossterm>auto_increment</glossterm>
		
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				Auto_increment is an option which can be applied on integer primary keys.
				It keeps track of the latest identification that was added and
				automatically assigns the following number on a new row (this is provided the
				row doesn't already have an identification).
			</para>
			
			<example>
				<title>Auto increment in the database</title>
				
				<para>
					We assume that the table has a few columns and an auto increment <literal>id</literal>
					column.
				</para>
				
				<programlisting language="SQL"><![CDATA[SELECT * FROM table;

-- id  ...
-- 1   ...

INSERT INTO table SET ...;

SELECT * FROM table;

-- id  ...
-- 1   ...
-- 2   ...

INSERT INTO table SET ...;

SELECT * FROM table;

-- id  ...
-- 1   ...
-- 2   ...
-- 3   ...]]></programlisting>
			</example>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	
	<glossentry xml:id="glossary.autoloader">
		<glossterm>autoloader</glossterm>
		
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				An autoloader is a function/method which PHP calls when a class or interface is missing (ie. not included).
				The task of the autoloader is to load the specified class/interface.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				If the autoloader is successful, execution continues just as if the file already was included.
				But if the autoloader fails to include the class/interface, PHP dies with a missing class/interface error as usual.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Autoloaders can also be chained, so that if one autoloader doesn't find the requested class,
				other autoloaders get their shot at it.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	
	<glossentry xml:id="glossary.callback">
		<glossterm>callback</glossterm>
		
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				A callback is a value which can be treated as a reference to a method or function.
				Sort of like function pointers.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Examples:
			</para>
			
			<example>
				<title>Examples of different callbacks</title>
				
				<programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[// reference to trim()
$function_callback = 'trim';

// MyClass::myMethod()
$static_method_callback = 'MyClass::myMethod';
// or
$static_method_callback = array('MyClass', 'myMethod');

// $instance->method()
$c = new MyClass();
$method_callback = array($c, 'method');

// closure:
$closure = function()
{
	return 'foo';
};]]></programlisting>
			</example>
			
			<para>
				To call a callback, one either appends parenthesis on the variable name (<literal>$name()</literal>),
				this is used by string-based callbacks and closures.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				To be able to call all types of callbacks, one usually uses <function>call_user_func()</function>
				or <function>call_user_func_array()</function>.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	
	<glossentry xml:id="glossary.code_builder">
		<glossterm>code builder</glossterm>
		
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				A code builder is a piece of program which generates code to be compiled/executed at a later stage.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Code builders can be used because of several reasons, the reasons RapidDataMapper uses them are:
			</para>
			
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Speed: The code is optimized for the objects which are mapped,
						the code is then cached which removes the need to rebuild the code on the following requests.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Customizability: The generated code can be modified by the user-controlled descriptor objects.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	
	<glossentry xml:id="glossary.descriptor">
		<glossterm>descriptor</glossterm>
		
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				An object describing how a PHP class should be mapped to the database.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				It also controls the whole code creation process, instantiating the code builders and supplying the needed data.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	
	<glossentry xml:id="glossary.exception">
		<glossterm>exception</glossterm>
		
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				An object which is "thrown" upwards the call stack to signal an error.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				These objects can be intercepted and then proper actions can take place to either try to rectify the error
				or to terminate gracefully.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	
	<glossentry xml:id="glossary.mapper">
		<glossterm>mapper</glossterm>
		
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				A mapper is a class which contains the logic for inserting, deleting, updating and fetching data.
				The mapper is also the class which handles the relations.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				The mappers are managed by the <classname>Db</classname> class, and usually you don't have to deal directly with them.
				In the case you want to operate directly on a mapper, you can fetch it by calling <function>Db::getMapper()</function>.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	
	<glossentry xml:id="glossary.method_chaining">
		<glossterm>method chaining</glossterm>
		
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				Method chaining is a new feature for PHP 5, which enables a programmer to call methods directly on
				returned objects without having to assign them to objects:
			</para>
			
			<example>
				<title>Method chaining vs. no method chaining</title>
				
				<programlisting language="php"><![CDATA[// not chained:
$db = Db::getConnection();
$query = $db->select();
$query->from('users');
$result = $query->get();

// chained:
$result = Db::getConnection()->select()->from('users')->get();]]></programlisting>
				
				<para>
					The <function>Db_Query_Select->from()</function> method returns the object instance,
					which means that <function>get()</function> above was called on the same <classname>Db_Query_Select</classname>
					instance as <function>from()</function> was.
				</para>
			</example>
			
			<para>
				See <link linkend="chapter.query_builders">Query Builders</link> for more information and examples.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	
	<glossentry xml:id="glossary.orm">
		<glossterm>Object-Relational-Mapper</glossterm>
		
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				A term used to describe a library which maps object-data to a relational database.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
	
	<glossentry xml:id="glossary.primary_key">
		<glossterm>primary key</glossterm>
		
		<glossdef>
			<para>
				A key (column) in the database which contains unique identifiers for the rows in a table.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				A primary key can also be composed out of several columns and is then called a composite primary key.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
	</glossentry>
</glossary>